Finding Aid for the Alois Reiser Papers PASC-M.0006
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alois Reiser papers
1871-1957
UCLA Library Special Collections
Reiser, Alois
PASC-M.0006
8.2 Linear Feet (4 document boxes, 14 flat boxes and 1 oversize flat box.)
This collection consists of the sheet music manuscripts of Czech cellist, composer, and film music director Alois Reiser. These materials span Reiser's entire career and include his classical compositions, operas, materials from his time as conductor at New York's Strand Theater, and work as a composer and music director for the film industry in Los Angeles. Also included are screenplays for various films, newspaper clippings of publicity for Reiser, some published material, and a few photographs.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9927230593606533
Biography
Reiser (born on April 6, 1887) was a Czech composer and cellist. Born in Prague, Reiser studied with Antonín Dvorák at the Prague Conservatory and received his doctorate of music at the University of Prague. Reiser also took cello lessons and toured Europe and the United States as a concert cellist with the Bohemian Trio, also performing for a time as a cellist with the Pittsburgh and New York Symphony Orchestras. Afterward, Reiser reestablished himself in Prague and became conductor Prague Opera House. Returning to New York in 1918, he worked as a conductor at the Strand Theater until 1929, when he moved to Hollywood to work as a composer and musical director for film studios. At Warner Bros. and, later, Fox Studios, he worked on films such as Noah's Ark (1928), Her Private Life (1929), Spring Is Here (1930), The Millionaire (1931), and Caravan (1934). His classical compositions include the opera Gobi (1912), Concerto for cello and orchestra (1916), String quartet in E minor (1916), Little Coquette (1918), From Mount Rainier (1926), Slavic Rhapsody (1927), Trio in F major (1931), and Erewhon (1931). He died on April 4, 1977 in Los Angeles.
Scope and Content
This collection predominantly consists of manuscripts and holographic sketches of Reiser's orchestral, operatic, chamber and film music. Sheet music includes full scores, miniature scores, parts, vocal scores, and lead sheets. Also included are film scripts and treatments, some published works, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series: Series 1. Orchestral works; Series 2. Operas; Series 3. Songs for voice and piano; Series 4. Chamber music; Series 5. Film music; Subseries 5.1. Film scores; Subseries 5.2. Scripts and Treatments; Series 6. Personal materials.
Music -- Manuscripts.; Motion picture music -- Scores.; Composers -- Archives.; Reiser, Alois -- Archives
- Orchestral Works, 1871-1937; Series 1.
  Scope and Content
  This series contains full scores and individual parts for orchestral pieces composed by Reiser. The scores bear annotations and corrections, though finished scores are included as well. All scores are manuscripts or manuscript facsimiles, unless otherwise noted.
  - Concert for Cello and Orchestra in D, Op. 7, by Johan S. Svendsen (printed sheet music), 1871 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Concerto for Cello and Orchestra in D, Op. 14 (full scores, short scores and parts), 1916, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Erewhon: A Symphonic Poem, Op. 19 (full scores and parts), circa 1931 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - Slavic Rhapsody (full scores and parts), 1927-1937 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Summer Evening: A Symphonic Idyll, Op. 8 (full score and parts), circa 1907 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Symphony in 3 Parts: Fate, Unknown, Joy (full scores and parts), undated (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
  - Symphony No. 1 (parts for violin), undated (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
- Operas, 1912-1927; Series 2.
  This series contains full scores, vocal scores, and instrumental parts for various of Reiser's operas. Contents are manuscripts and manuscript facsimiles, unless otherwise noted. They include rough drafts, sketches, bear annotations and corrections but also include final scores.
  - Daphne (sketches and finished scores), undated (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Gobi and Prelude to Act III of Gobi (sketches, parts, and printed scores), 1912, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 1-5, Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Prelude to Gobi (Iris) (full scores and parts), [circa 1912] (Box 7, Folder 2-6)
- Songs for Voice and Piano, [circa 1910]-1942; Series 3.
  This series contains drafts, sketches, and finished copies of scores and lead sheets for songs composed by Reiser. All contents are manuscripts or manuscript facsimiles, unless otherwise noted.
  Due to intermixing of titled and untitled manuscripts, no attempt to separate titles has been made for this series. Titles of works found in each folder have been included under the folder heading.
  - Manuscripts (1 of 6), undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Includes: Love is All That Matters, When We Truly Love, and Youth.
  - Manuscripts (2 of 6), circa 1942 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Includes: Down in the Canary Isles, I Found a Dream, Spanish Blues (Love Song), We're Gonna Collect (includes printed sheet music), Ye Beauty Shoppe, and various untitled manuscripts.
  - Manuscripts (3 of 6), 1920s-1942 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Includes: Always Remember, Bersaglieri, Compensation, Don't Wait for Love, Down Where the Wild Desert Blooms, If, In the Garden At Dawning, It Is Not Always May, It Wasn't Any Business for a Lady, I've an Alibi, Love Can See, Love's Ecstasy, Musical Comedy, My Heart is Yours!, My Sweetheart, Nerida, Song of the Clock, Tapestry Symphony, Valse Concertante, Valse Romance, Valse Lente, Waltz With Me Tonight, When You Come Home, Who Do You Love?, and an untitled song typescript.
  - Manuscripts (4 of 6), undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Includes: Blue Moon (Valsette), Dream, How Could I Know, Jeanette, The Lord is My Shepherd, Love Me Little, Love Me Long, Maureen, O Dream So Blissful, Something Tells Me, Two Songs (Op.6), Vola (Spanish Romance), Wondrous Ship, and various untitled manuscripts.
  - Manuscripts (5 of 6), undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Includes largely untitled manuscripts in a folder titled "Sketches".
  - Manuscripts (6 of 6), circa 1910 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Full score for Three Ballads of François Villon by Claude Debussy, arranged by Reiser.
- Chamber Music, 1919-1930s; Series 4.
  This series contains scores for Reiser's chamber music compositions All contents are manuscripts or manuscript facsimiles, unless otherwise noted. They include rough drafts, sketches, bear annotations and corrections but also include final scores.
  - Quartet for Strings in E Minor, Op. 16 (printed sheet music), 1919-1920 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Sonata for Violin and Piano, Op. 20 (bound manuscript facsim. with annotations), undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - String Quartet in C, Op. 18 (scores, parts, and facsimiles), circa 1930 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - String Quartet No.3 (score and parts), 1930s (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Trio in E Minor for Piano, Violin, and Cello, Op. 12 (score and parts), undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Trio in F for Piano, Violin, and Cello, Op. 17 (score and parts), circa 1931 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Film Music, 1920s-1957; Series 5.
  This series includes manuscript scores for films that Reiser worked on, as well as scripts and treatments for later films, which may or may not have passed into production.
  - Film Scores, 1920s-1940s; Subseries 5.1.
    Drafts, sketches, full scores and parts for various films. Include transition and theme music, scene music, and orchestral works for film. Scores are manuscripts or manuscript facsimiles, unless otherwise noted. Most bear annotations and corrections.
    - Bacchanale, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Bali film: compiled scenes and structure notes, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
      Includes scene lists and scores from a film set in Bali; possibly Man's Paradise, an ethnographic documentary about Bali shot in 1932 and released in 1938.
    - Scene: Bali Dance, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Scene: Bali Idyll, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Scene: Bali Intermezzo, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Scene: Bali Temple, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Scene: Bali Theme, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Scene: The Cockfight, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Scene: Cocoanuts Intermezzo, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Scene: Dancing Girl, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Scene: Denaturing the Evil Spirits, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Scene: Dragon Fight and the Puppet Show, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Scene: Java Dance, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Scene: Market, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Scenes: Melody, Phili Dance, Pigs, Turtle Soup, and untitled manuscripts, circa 1932 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Caravane/ Csardas, circa 1934 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Chink Walk (includes printed sheet music), 1929 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Die Fledermaus (The Bat), operetta by J. Strauss (script for Reiser's adaptation), undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - From Mount Rainier, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - The Magic Lamp, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - Serenata and Spirit of Spring, circa 1921 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Various, circa 1928 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Includes: Love and Passion (Appassionata D'Amour) (printed sheet music), Entre Nous (parts), Six Czech Folk Songs. Manuscript scores for Careers (1929), The Millionaire (1931), Star Witness (1931), and other unspecified films.
  - Scripts and Treatments, 1930-1957; Subseries 5.2.
    Drafts, completed scripts, treatments, and synopses for various films.
    - Bellevue Is My Home, 1957 April 26 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - The Black Forest, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - By The Night Star, 1947 April 16-May 8 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - The Deserter, 1950 April 6-1956 May 22 (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
    - Esther, 1950-1951 (Box 16, Folder 2-7)
    - The Fatal Wedding, 1930 October 20-1931 February 17 (Box 18, Folder 3-6)
    - Modesta, 1949 February 22-1950 April 4 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
    - That Night At Shepheard's, 1945 January 4 (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Personal Materials, 1910- 1937; Series 6.
  This series largely includes newspaper clippings and magazine issues in which Reiser is mentioned, as well as a CV and three photographs.
  - Newspaper clippings about Reiser, 1910-1937 (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
  - Strand Theater program for screening of Charlie Chaplin's The Circus, orch. accompaniment conducted by Reiser, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Issue of Musical America with article about Reiser's Quartet for Strings, Op. 16. 1920 November 13. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Issue of the Musical Observer, Vol. 20, 1921 April (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Issue of The Brooklyn Standard Union featuring Reiser, 1923 March 11 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - CV and photographs, circa 1936 (Box 15, Folder 8)